Guide to the Joseph Spence Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Notes & Memoranda, Series IV
  - England: History of, notes and materials on (Box 4, Folder 83)
    Includes; Copy of messages between George II and Frederick Louis in 1737 Material on Battle of Dettingen Copy of a letter from a Jesuit close to the crown in 1687 Copy, in Spence's hand, of a letter to George II. Copy of a Latin panegyric to Charles I An account of the history of invasions of England And other materials
    See also: London, Box 4, folder 98
  - England: Travel memorabilia (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - England and Scotland, travel notes relating to landscapes and gardening (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Europe, History and Travel, notes on (Box 4, Folder 86)
    See also: Italy (here excluded), Box 4, folder 95
  - Fleetwood, William, bp. of Ely, 1656-1723
    - Preface to his Four Sermons, 1712., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - Friends of Spence, notes on histories of, and documents
    - Misc. material, unsorted, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - Mallet, David
    - Epilogue to The Brothers, by Edward Young. spoken by Mrs. Clive. Docketed by Spence, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Greece, History, notes on, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - Herbert, N., b. 1688
    - Poetry and a riddle (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - Herculaneum, notes on antiquities of, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - (heading notes date from volumes of 1757-60)
  - See also Roman, or Italy, various subtopics.
  - Hill, Jonathan
    - Items relating to Spence's support of, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 93)
      Includes: Spence's notes on Hill; a proposal for a printing of poetry by subscription, 1758.
  - Iliad, a calendar of the passage of time in (Box 4, Folder 94)
  - Presumably notes for Spence's Essay on Pope's Odyssey, 1726.
  - Italy: History of, notes on, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 95)
  - Italy: Travel notes, with some epitaphs, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 96)
  - Lawman, Harry
    - Poetry by (Lawman was a cousin of Spence), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 97)
  - London: misc. (Box 4, Folder 98)
  - Louis IV, 1638-1715
    - Notes on the life of, from Larrey [Isaac de?], a life of Louis IV, [ca. 1783] (Box 4, Folder 99)
  - Low, John, (active 1763)
    - The story of, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 100)
  - Lyttelton, George Lyttelton, 1st baron, 1709-1773:
    - Poetry by, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 101)
  - Medicine and Health, reading notes on (Box 4, Folder 102)
  - Miscellaneous quaint items, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 103)
  - Miscellaneous note wrappers, accounts, and lists of expenses (Box 4, Folder 104)
  - Mogul Empire, notes on history of, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 105)
  - Morality, Chinese: notes on, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 106)
  - Music, with lyrics, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 107)
  - Neville, Henry, 1620-1694
    - Poetry of and notes about (Box 4, Folder 108)
    - (Colonel H. Neville was a distant relative of Spence on his mother's side.)
  - Ossian's poetry, tr. by MacPherson, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 109)
  - Ovid: list of Select Stories from, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 110)
  - Preliminary notes toward an edition of Ovid's stories.
  - Oxford, a notice concerning the teaching of religion at, 1728 (Box 4, Folder 111)
  - Philosophy, reading in
    - From Giordano Bruno, 1548-1600), Degli evoici furori, (1585), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 112)
  - Poetry, English, misc., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 113)
  - Including poems by "Mr Moore", "Joseph Spence, Sr.", "Miss Jones", "Miss Herbert", "Harison", "Mr Harding", "Mr Fitzgerald", "Christ. Neville", "Dr Byron", "Bp Downes", "Mrs Aldworth", "Mr Hooke", "Halifax" and others.
    See also: poetry filed under individual authors.
  - Poetry, in French, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 114)
  - Possible authors are Dr. Arbuthnot, Edward Holdsworth, and Middlesex fragment in Italian on back of French poem).
  - Poetry, French, reading notes on, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 115)
  - Poetry, in Greek, and translations of (Box 4, Folder 116)
  - Poetry, in Italian, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 117)
  - Poetry, in Latin, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 118)
  - Some may be by Spence, esp. those which appear to be corrected in his hand.
  - Poetry, Latin, translated into English, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 119)
  - Pope, Alexander, 1688-1744
    - Early plans for Ethic Epistles (1734), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 120)
    - Events of his life, from Epistle to Arbuthnot, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 121)
    - Lists of his works, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 122)
  - Portsmouth, John Wallop, 1st earl of, d. 1762
    - Directions for a painting for him, probably of Lord Portsmouth's son, John Wallop, Viscount Lymington, 1718-1749, and his family [?]. (Box 5, Folder 123)
  - Prayers of famous persons, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 124)
  - Rabelais, François, ca. 1494-1553
    - Reading notes on, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 125)
  - Religion, notes on, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 126)
  - Notes on heathen religions, particularly Greek and Roman, and on history of Christian persecution and development of Christian beliefs.
  - Ridley, Gloster, 1702-1774
    - Poetry by. One copied from Melampus, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 127)
  - Rolle, Edward, 1703-1791
    - Poetry by, 1754 (Box 5, Folder 128)
  - Roman -- general reading in, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 129)
  - Materials which include diverse topics.
  - Roman Art and Architecture, reading in (Box 5, Folder 130)
  - Roman History and Government, reading in (Box 5, Folder 131)
  - Roman Literature, reading in, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 132)
  - St. Solomon, Job
    - Story of, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 133)
  - Spence, Joseph
    - Portrait of, with a cllpping, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 134)
  - Spence, Joseph: Writings
    - The Dream of Atticus, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 135)
    - "A dialogue, in the shades, between B and C." Apparently unpublished. Note by Spence to be burned at his death (Box 5, Folder 136)
    - A letter to Charles Easy, Drafts, with a second letter (Box 5, Folder 137)
    - Printed in the Museum vol I, p. 81 and in Moralities, p. 16. Second letter apparently unpublished
    - A translation from Erasmus on the Way to Continue Young, draft of, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 138)
    - Apparently unpublished, but, like the Dialogue between Mrs. Snap and Mrs. Easy, freely translated from a dialogue by Erasmus
    - Various Essays: On religion, the mind, learning, conversation, customs, and incidental topics; Ovid. Published? (Box 5, Folder 139)
    - Fables, drafts of:, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 140)
    - Apes and Weasels The Cat and her Young one Thc Gentleman and his Steward The Schoolmaster and Painter The Trout The Old Fisherwoman
    - Horsemanship among Greeks and Romans (Box 5, Folder 141)
    - Probably unpublished
    - Letters between a mother and her daughter (Box 5, Folder 142)
    - Published in Moralities, p. 54.
    - A preliminary list of works to be printed in Moralities, 1753, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 143)
    - Drafts of an advertisement for the forthcoming Polymetis, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 144)
    - Published in the Museum, 26 Apr 1746, Vol I.
    - History of Pericles, draft, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 145)
    - Published in Moralities, p. 1.
    - Notes toward the translation of the (Box 5, Folder 146)
    - Picture of Human Life by Cebes, n.d.
    - Notes from James Merrick, 1720-1769, in Merrick's hand. Picture of Human Life was published in Moralities, 1753, p. 146.
    - Plan for an Heroic Poem [?], n.d. (Box 5, Folder 147)
    - Poetry in English, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 148)
    - Poetry in Latin, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 149)
    - With various notes, on the poetry sheets.
    - A Presentation at Oxford, [1736] (Box 5, Folder 150)
    - Presenting Edward Noel, later Viscount Wentworth, 1715-1774, as recipient of M.A. degree. Noel attended New College, Oxford, was created M..A. on 19 Jul 1736.
    - Religious Fooleries, draft, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 151)
    - Revolution in an Emmet's Nest, copy, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 152)
    - Publ. in the Museum, vol. 1, p. 291, and in Moralities, p. 81.
  - Swift, Jonathan, 1667-1745
    - Poetry and prose (Box 5, Folder 153)
    - (Photostat story from Newcastle Papers at Nottingham.)
    - Spence's life of Swift: notes toward, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 154)
    - (photostats from the Newcastle Papers at Nottingham.)
  - Virgil
    - Laurel leaves gathered from the tomb of Virgil by Spence, 1732 (Box 5, Folder 155)
  - Winchester College
    - Matter of educating a new Warden of Winchester College, 1757 (Box 5, Folder 156)
    - Dispute between Dr. Cheyney and Dr. Fletcher (Box 5, Folder 157)
    - Mentions "Mr Lee" -- Harry Lee, Warden of Winchester College, 1721-1789.
  - Wycherley, William, 1640-1716
    - Account of early life of, from Pope, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 158)
- Gardening Notes, ca. 1754; Series V
  - Auckland Park: Bishop Butler, ca. 1754 (Box 5, Folder 159)
  - Bellasis, near Durham: Joseph Spence?, 1699-1768, 1762 Mar 2 (Box 5, Folder 160)
  - Reference to planting of trees at Bellasis in Spence's absence, letter of Lowth to Spence
  - Berwick St. John in Wiltshire: Edward Rolle, 1703-1791 or his agent [?] Mr. Foot, ca. 1756, 1761 (Box 5, Folder 161)
    Pencil notes on one sheet about Mr.
    Hoare's at Stourhead, Wiltshire.
  - Birchanger, in Essex: Joseph Spence, 1699-1768, ca. 1736-38 (Box 5, Folder 162)
  - on Bond Street in London: Noel Bruxholme, 1689?-1748, ca. 1743 (Box 5, Folder 163)
  - Buckingham Gate, a garden by, 1747 (Box 5, Folder 164)
  - Byfleet, in Surrey, plans for the Point, (presumably) at or near, 1752 (Box 5, Folder 165)
  - Byfleet in Surrey: Stephen Duck, 1705-1756, ca. 1752 (Box 5, Folder 166)
  - Byfleet in Surrey: Joseph Spence 1699- 1768, ca. 1748-64 (Box 6, Folder 167)
    Some plans may relate to areas of
    Byfleet belonging to others.
    The plans for the Nightingale Arbor
    are probably for Byfleet, though not
    definitely
    See also: other folders on Byfleet, and folder for Oatlands and adjacent lands, Box 1, folder 10
  - Chalford (or Shalford): Mr. Bartlemew, ca. 1762 (Box 6, Folder 168)
  - College Court at Durham, 1756 (Box 6, Folder 169)
  - Dalrymple: An Essay on Gardening, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 170)
  - Danson: Mr Lloyd, ca. 1763? (Box 6, Folder 171)
  - Dashwood, Samuel, estate of, 1761 (Box 6, Folder 172)
  - Dickins, Doctor, estate of, 1764 (Box 6, Folder 173)
  - Edwinstowe in Nottinghamshire: Duke of Newcastle or his agent [?] Mr Fisher, ca. 1763 (Box 6, Folder 174)
  - Exchequer House, plans for ground between it and the Thames, 1753 (Box 6, Folder 175)
  - Ferryhill: Mr Boleby, ca. 1766 (Box 6, Folder 176)
  - Fulham (London): Baron Atkyns, ca. 1763-66 (Box 6, Folder 177)
    House may by named Gil Blas.
    Reference to original design at
    Le Sage's house, Rue de St. Jacques,
    Paris
  - Glenham, in Suffolk: [Nicholas?] Herbert, 1768 (Box 6, Folder 178)
  - Great Horwood, in Buckingham: Joseph Spence, 1699-1768, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 179)
  - Hillenden: General Herbert, ca. 1753? (Box 6, Folder 180)
  - Inchberd, Captain, estate of, 1754 (Box 6, Folder 181)
  - Jackson, Dr., ideas from his estate, 1765 (Box 6, Folder 182)
  - Johnson, General, estate of, ca. 1753? (Box 6, Folder 183)
  - Kimbolton Castle in Huntingdonshire: Duke of Manchester, ca. 1745-46? (Box 6, Folder 184)
  - Kirkby Mallory, in Leicester: Edward Noel, viscount Wentworth, 1715-1774, or Mr Noel (agent or relative?), ca. 1757, 1766 (Box 6, Folder 185)
  - Knole, in Kent: Charles Sackville, 2nd duke of Dorset, 1711-1769, 1766 (Box 6, Folder 186)
  - Leasowes near Birmingham: William Shenstone, 1714-1763, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 187)
  - London town house: Lady Falmouth, 1744 (Box 6, Folder 188)
  - Moore, Mr, in Surrey, ca. 1763 (Box 6, Folder 189)
  - Oatlands, in Surrey, and adjacent lands: Henry Fiennes Clinton, 2nd duke of Newcastle, 1720-1794, 1748, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 190)
    Plans for Garden Grove, labled
    "Continiatopm", for Mr Moody, 1748,
    appear to be for Mr. Moody at
    Oatlands, Newcastle's agent.
    Sheets referring to "Plantation"
    seem to be for part of Oatlands,
    or Byfleet, in Surrey.
  - Ormesby, in Lincolnshire: William Massingberd, 1719-1802, 1756-65 (Box 6, Folder 191)
  - Paul, Thomas, Dean of Cashel, ca. 1765 (Box 6, Folder 192)
  - Pauler's Perry: Mr. Alston, ca. 1757? (Box 6, Folder 193)
  - Persfield: Mr. Morris, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 194)
  - Prestonfield, near Edinburgh: Sir Alexander Dick 1703-1785, ca. 1764? (Box 6, Folder 195)
  - Raby Castle: Henry Vane, 2nd earl of Darlington, ca. 1705-1758, 1755 (Box 6, Folder 196)
  - Rem'nham; Dr. Morgan, 1766 (Box 6, Folder 197)
  - Richmond: Robert Dodsley, 1703-1764, ca. 1753 (Box 6, Folder 198)
  - Richmond: Mr. Knipe, 1753 (Box 6, Folder 199)
  - Sedgefield, near Durham: Robert Lowth, bp. of London, 1710-1787, ca. 1756 (Box 6, Folder 200)
  - Southcote, Philip, 1699?-1758, his manner of planting, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 201)
  - Stourton (Stourhead?), in Wiltshire: Henry Hoare, 1705-1785, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 202)
  - Stratton Street, in London: Joseph Spence, 1699-1768, 1744 (Box 6, Folder 203)
  - Walker, Mr.: An Essay on Planting Sent to Spence by Sir Alexander Dick (Box 6, Folder 204)
  - Wardour Castle, in Wiltshire: Lord Arundel (Box 6, Folder 205)
  - Wheatfield, in Oxfordshire: Edward Rudge, ca. 1765 (Box 6, Folder 206)
  - White-Harte, at Missenden, 1752? (Box 6, Folder 207)
  - Whitton: Duke of Argyle (Box 6, Folder 208)
  - Wood, Mr., designs from, ca. 1749 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Writle: Mr. Eyre, 1763 (Box 6, Folder 210)
  - Materials for Designing a Garden: plant lists, general rules to follow, n.d. (Box 11 (Broadside))
  - Miscellaneous Items of interest to one whose hobby is gardening, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 212)
  - Garden Plans, Unidentified, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 213)
  - Reading Notes on Gardening, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 214)
- Miscellaneous and Indexes, Series VI
  - Huntington Ms. of Spence's Anecdotes (Box 7, Folder 215)
  - Source "W" B.M. Egerton Ms. l960 (Box 7, Folder 216)
  - Notes sent by Spence to Warburton 8 folio leaves (Box 7, Folder 217)
  - Miscellaneous. "Mr. P's 3 great Escapes ... " (Box 7, Folder 218)
  - Supplemental anecdotes, compiled by Singer (Box 7, Folder 219)
  - Earlier Worksheets used on Spence Papers (Box 7, Folder 220)
  - Huntington Ms of Spence's Anecdotes, the Index to (Box 7, Folder 221)
  - Sale Catalogue of Spence Papers (Box 7, Folder 222)
  - Index of Names Appearing in Spence Papers With dates and known residences. (Box 7, Folder 223)
- Loose Papers for the Anecdotes, Series VII
  - L1 - L 53 (Box 7, Folder 224-277)
  - Also A Catalogue of the Entire Libraries of The Rev. Mr. Joseph Spence ... (photocopy), 1769 Aug 8, in large manila envelope
  - See: Series VIII
- Derby Anecdotes (Oversize), Series VIII
  - Volume I (Box 8, Folder 278)
  - Volume II (Box 9, Folder 279)
  - Volume III (Box 10, Folder 280)
  - A Catalogue of the Entire Libraries of The Rev. Mr. Joseph Spence (photocopy), n.d. (Box 10, Folder 281)